<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> 
  <channel>
    <title>SPC Forecast Products</title>
    <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/</link>
    <description>Storm Prediction Center</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>None</copyright>
    <managingEditor>spc.feedback@noaa.gov (spc.feedback@noaa.gov)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>spc.feedback@noaa.gov (spc.feedback@noaa.gov)</webMaster>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:46:01 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:46:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <rating>general</rating>
    <docs>http://validator.w3.org/feed/rss2.html</docs>
    <ttl>1</ttl>
    <atom:link href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/spcrss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    <image>
      <url>http://weather.gov/images/xml_logo.gif</url>
      <title>SPC Forecast Products</title>
      <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/</link>
    </image> 

    <item>
      <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163.html</link>
      <title>SPC Tornado Watch 163</title>
      <description>WW 163 TORNADO IA NE 301835Z - 010300Z
      <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163_radar.gif" border="1" alt="WW 0163 Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="525" height="459" align="center" /></a><pre>

URGENT - IMMEDIATE BROADCAST REQUESTED
Tornado Watch Number 163
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
135 PM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

The NWS Storm Prediction Center has issued a

* Tornado Watch for portions of 
  Southern and Western Iowa
  Eastern Nebraska

* Effective this Tuesday afternoon and evening from 135 PM until
  1000 PM CDT.

* Primary threats include...
  A few tornadoes possible
  Scattered damaging winds and isolated significant gusts to 80
    mph likely
  Scattered large hail and isolated very large hail events to 2.5
    inches in diameter likely

SUMMARY...Severe thunderstorms will develop this afternoon over
eastern Nebraska and track eastward across the watch area through
the evening.

The tornado watch area is approximately along and 60 statute miles
north and south of a line from 50 miles north northwest of Lincoln
NE to 35 miles east of Knoxville IA. For a complete depiction of the
watch see the associated watch outline update (WOUS64 KWNS WOU3).

PRECAUTIONARY/PREPAREDNESS ACTIONS...

REMEMBER...A Tornado Watch means conditions are favorable for
tornadoes and severe thunderstorms in and close to the watch
area. Persons in these areas should be on the lookout for
threatening weather conditions and listen for later statements
and possible warnings.

&&

AVIATION...Tornadoes and a few severe thunderstorms with hail
surface and aloft to 2.5 inches. Extreme turbulence and surface wind
gusts to 70 knots. A few cumulonimbi with maximum tops to 500. Mean
storm motion vector 27035.

...Hart

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163.html">Read more</a>
]]>
      </description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163.html/20240430</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ws0163.html</link>
      <title>SPC Tornado Watch 163 Status Reports</title>
      <description>WW 0163 Status Updates
      <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ws0163.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ww0163_radar.gif" border="1" alt="WW 0163 Status Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="525" height="459" align="center" /></a><pre>

STATUS REPORT ON WW 163

THE SEVERE WEATHER THREAT CONTINUES ACROSS THE ENTIRE WATCH AREA.

..LYONS..04/30/24

ATTN...WFO...DMX...OAX...FSD...


STATUS REPORT FOR WT 163 

SEVERE WEATHER THREAT CONTINUES FOR THE FOLLOWING AREAS 

IAC001-003-007-009-015-025-027-029-039-047-049-051-053-071-073-
077-085-093-099-117-121-123-125-129-133-135-137-145-153-155-157-
159-161-165-169-173-175-179-181-185-193-302040-

IA 
.    IOWA COUNTIES INCLUDED ARE

ADAIR                ADAMS               APPANOOSE           
AUDUBON              BOONE               CALHOUN             
CARROLL              CASS                CLARKE              
CRAWFORD             DALLAS              DAVIS               
DECATUR              FREMONT             GREENE              
GUTHRIE              HARRISON            IDA                 
JASPER               LUCAS               MADISON             
MAHASKA              MARION              MILLS               
MONONA               MONROE              MONTGOMERY          
PAGE                 POLK                POTTAWATTAMIE       
POWESHIEK            RINGGOLD            SAC                 
SHELBY               STORY               TAYLOR              
UNION                WAPELLO             WARREN              
WAYNE                WOODBURY            


NEC021-023-025-037-039-043-053-055-109-119-131-141-151-153-155-
159-167-173-177-302040-

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ws0163.html">Read more</a>
]]>
      </description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/watch/ws0163.html/2024043019</guid>
    </item>
      <item>
        <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0576.html</link>
        <title>SPC MD 576</title>
        <description>MD 0576 CONCERNING SEVERE POTENTIAL...WATCH POSSIBLE FOR PARTS OF EASTERN KANSAS
        <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0576.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/mcd0576.png" border="1" alt="MD 0576 Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="611" align="center" /></a><pre>

Mesoscale Discussion 0576
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
0235 PM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Areas affected...parts of eastern Kansas

Concerning...Severe potential...Watch possible 

Valid 301935Z - 302130Z

Probability of Watch Issuance...60 percent

SUMMARY...Intensifying thunderstorm development is probable through
4-7 PM CDT, including a few supercells with potential to produce
large hail, locally damaging wind gusts and a risk for tornadoes.

DISCUSSION...To the south of a strong, broadly cyclonic mid/upper
jet nosing east of the Front Range, toward the the middle Missouri
Valley, warm elevated mixed-layer air remains inhibitive to
convective development in the presence of weak to negligible
mid/upper forcing for ascent.  However, where the cold front is
overtaking a sharpening dryline across the Salina vicinity of north
central Kansas, more notable deepening of convective development is
ongoing.  

Aided by a corridor of stronger pre-frontal boundary-layer heating,
including surface temperatures exceeding 90F along an axis across
northwestern Oklahoma into the Salina vicinity, mixed-layer CAPE now
appears in excess of 2000 J/kg along the sharpening dryline.  With
additional insolation, it appears that low-level forcing near the
cold front/dryline intersection may become sufficient to support
sustained thunderstorm development as early as 21-22Z.  In the
presence of moderate but veering flow with height in the 850-500 mb
layer, vertical shear will be conducive to supercell development, at
 least initially, and perhaps an upscale growing line with
persistent supercell development along its southern flank, gradually
approaching the Wichita area through early evening.

..Kerr/Hart.. 04/30/2024

...Please see www.spc.noaa.gov for graphic product...

ATTN...WFO...EAX...TOP...ICT...OUN...DDC...

LAT...LON   38499761 39979640 39699511 37819607 36929748 37309836
            38499761 

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0576.html">Read more</a>
]]>
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:46:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0576.html/20240430</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0575.html</link>
        <title>SPC MD 575</title>
        <description>MD 0575 CONCERNING SEVERE POTENTIAL...WATCH POSSIBLE FOR PARTS OF EASTERN SOUTH DAKOTA...NORTHERN IOWA AND SOUTHERN MINNESOTA
        <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0575.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/mcd0575.png" border="1" alt="MD 0575 Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="611" align="center" /></a><pre>

Mesoscale Discussion 0575
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
0229 PM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Areas affected...parts of eastern South Dakota...Northern Iowa and
southern Minnesota

Concerning...Severe potential...Watch possible 

Valid 301929Z - 302130Z

Probability of Watch Issuance...40 percent

SUMMARY...Scattered thunderstorms over eastern SD may grow upscale
into a more organized line/cluster with time. Damaging winds and
hail are possible, but the coverage and severity are uncertain. A
Severe Thunderstorm Watch is possible.

DISCUSSION...Ahead of the advancing shortwave trough, thunderstorms
have initiated along a pre-frontal trough/convergence zone across
parts of eastern SD and northeastern NE. North of a modifying
outflow boundary/effective warm front, the air mass has slowly
moistened and warmed into the low 60s F. While not overly unstable,
heating through scattered cloud breaks and further moistening will
continue to allow for destabilization with SPC mesoanalysis showing
~500-1000 J/kg of MUCAPE. Effective straight-line hodographs will
favor a linear/cluster mode with further upscale growth from storm
interactions likely. Given the storm mode and modest buoyancy,
damaging winds appear to be the most likely threat. However,
occasional hail and a brief tornado will also be possible with any
embedded supercell/bowing structures able to develop. Buoyancy
decreases farther east indicating some uncertainty on the coverage
and timing of the severe risk. Still, mesoscale trends suggest
further destabilization is likely and a downstream severe risk may
develop. With this in mind, a Severe Thunderstorm Watch is possible.

..Lyons/Hart.. 04/30/2024

...Please see www.spc.noaa.gov for graphic product...

ATTN...WFO...ARX...MPX...DMX...FSD...OAX...

LAT...LON   42249290 42419701 42539722 43629719 44289665 44089414
            43779337 43299248 43179231 42969236 42399253 42309263
            42249290 

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0575.html">Read more</a>
]]>
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:46:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/md/md0575.html/20240430</guid>
      </item>
    <item>
      <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day1otlk_1630.html</link>
      <title>SPC Apr 30, 2024 1630 UTC Day 1 Convective Outlook</title>
      <description>SPC 1630Z Day 1 Outlook
      <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day1otlk.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day1otlk.gif" border="1" alt="Day 1 Outlook Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="555" align="center" /></a><pre>
Day 1 Convective Outlook  
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
1129 AM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Valid 301630Z - 011200Z

...THERE IS AN ENHANCED RISK OF SEVERE THUNDERSTORMS THIS AFTERNOON
AND EVENING ACROSS PARTS OF WESTERN IOWA...SOUTHEAST
NEBRASKA...NORTHEAST KANSAS...AND NORTHWEST MISSOURI...

...SUMMARY...
The greatest threat for severe weather (large hail, severe gusts,
and a few tornadoes) is from western and central Iowa to
northeastern Kansas.

...Eastern NE/Western IA/Northwest MO/Northeast KS...
Water vapor loops show a fast-moving shortwave trough and associated
mid/upper level speed max moving across the central Rockies into the
Plains.  Ahead of this trough, southerly low-level winds are
transporting moisture northward with dewpoints in the 60s now as far
north as southeast NE.  Continued daytime heating and moisture
advection will lead to a narrow corridor of moderate CAPE over
eastern NE by mid-afternoon.  A consensus of morning model guidance
indicated that thunderstorms will form in this regime, with other
intense storms developing southward along the surface cold front
into northeast KS by late afternoon.  Forecast soundings show shear
profiles favorable for supercell structures capable of very large
hail and a few tornadoes.  After dark, these storms are expected to
congeal into one or more bowing structures that will track eastward
into central IA/northern MO with a greater risk of damaging wind
gusts along with hail and perhaps tornadoes.

...Eastern KS/Western OK/Northwest TX...
The surface dryline will extend southward from northeast KS into
northwest OK and northwest TX.  Isolated intense storms are expected
from roughly Wichita northward, with decreasing confidence from
there southward.  Weak large scale forcing, rising mid level
heights, and generally warming temperatures at 700mb suggest any
storms that form along the dryline will be widely scattered. 
However, large CAPE values, steep mid level lapse rates, and
sufficient vertical shear will support supercell structures capable
of all severe hazards in any storm that can form/sustain.  Will
maintain the ongoing SLGT/MRGL areas at this time, but will
reevaluate at 20z.

...NY/PA...
Strong daytime heating is occurring over areas from central NY into
central PA, where dewpoints are in the upper 50s.  Forecast
soundings suggest afternoon MLCAPE values of 500-1000 J/kg, leading
to scattered afternoon thunderstorms.  Low-level winds are
relatively weak/veered, but sufficient winds aloft and steep
low-level lapse rates could contribute to a risk of gusty/damaging
wind gusts and hail in the strongest cells this afternoon.

..Hart/Lyons.. 04/30/2024

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day1otlk.html">Read more</a>
]]>
      </description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 16:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day1otlk_1630.html/202404301946</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day2otlk_1730.html</link>
      <title>SPC Apr 30, 2024 1730 UTC Day 2 Convective Outlook</title>
      <description>SPC 1730Z Day 2 Outlook
      <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day2otlk.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day2otlk.gif" border="1" alt="Day 2 Outlook Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="555" align="center" /></a><pre>
Day 2 Convective Outlook  
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
1234 PM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Valid 011200Z - 021200Z

...THERE IS AN ENHANCED RISK OF SEVERE THUNDERSTORMS IN A PART OF
SOUTHWEST KS TO NORTHWEST OK...

...SUMMARY...
Scattered severe thunderstorms are possible across parts of the
central and southern Great Plains from Wednesday afternoon into
Wednesday night. A few tornadoes, very large hail, and damaging
winds are anticipated.

...Synopsis...
In the wake of a vigorous shortwave trough moving across the Upper
Great Lakes to the Saint Lawrence Valley, an upstream shortwave
impulse will gradually shift east from the northern Rockies to the
northern High Plains. The initial cold front on D1 over the central
Great Plains will stall and advance north as a warm front Wednesday
night. Convective outflows from residual D1/early D2 convection
should exist south of this boundary in parts of OK. 

...Central Great Plains...
Consensus of guidance continues to trend south with the placement of
the quasi-stationary front expected to be lying across southern KS
at 12Z Wednesday. A pronounced low-level jet should restrengthen
during the day, which will probably yield a swath of elevated
convection spreading northeast across the Mid-MO Valley with perhaps
a marginal severe hail threat. How far north the front will advance
during the day is uncertain with above-average spread across
guidance, but near its intersection with the surface dryline in the
southwest to west-central KS vicinity should be the most favorable
combination of the thermodynamic/kinematic environment. With
near-neutral mid-level height change through early evening,
convergence along the dryline will be necessary for late afternoon
thunderstorm development. Guidance largely suggests convective
coverage will remain isolated at most. But within a highly favorable
environment for supercells, tornadoes and very large hail will be
possible. 

On Wednesday evening into the night, the plume of returning
low-level moisture coupled with increasing large-scale ascent
downstream of the northern Rockies to High Plains should lead to
largely elevated storms developing in the CO/NE/KS border vicinity.
Much of this convection should remain north-northwest of the surface
warm front and likely remain elevated until very late in the period.
But with very steep lapse rates aloft, a strong low-level jet and
strong forcing for ascent, an elevated MCS capable of producing both
large hail and severe surface wind gusts remains possible. 

...Southern Great Plains...
Strong heating will occur near the dryline, where an uncapped and
very unstable air mass will develop with MLCAPE of 3000-3500 J/kg.
Bulk of guidance suggests appreciable convective development will
occur in west TX, where a minor mid-level impulse may emerge within
the modest southern-stream flow regime. More isolated dryline storms
should form farther north, perhaps intersecting with residual
outflows from remnant convection in OK on Wednesday morning. 

Deep-layer shear compared to early May climo will be relatively
modest, but the ample buoyancy coupled with numerous storms should
yield a mixed cluster and transient/slow-moving supercell mode.
Large to significant severe hail and sporadic severe wind gusts will
be possible. Potential will exist for upscale growth into
slow-moving clusters that move east into central parts of TX during
the evening and likely linger overnight, with a gradually subsiding
severe threat during these time frames.

..Grams.. 04/30/2024

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day2otlk.html">Read more</a>
]]>
      </description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 17:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/outlook/day2otlk_1730.html/202404301946</guid>
    </item>
        <item>
          <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy1.html</link>
          <title>SPC Day 1 Fire Weather Outlook</title>
          <description>SPC Day 1 Fire Weather Outlook
          <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy1.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/day1fireotlk.gif" border="1" alt="Day 1 Fire Weather Outlook Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="555" align="center" /></a><pre>
Day 1 Fire Weather Outlook  
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
1123 AM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Valid 301700Z - 011200Z

Trimmed the northeast portion of the Elevated area based on forecast
frontal position today. Otherwise, the forecast remains on track.
See previous discussion below.

..Bentley.. 04/30/2024

.PREV DISCUSSION... /ISSUED 0110 AM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024/

...Synopsis...
A belt of enhanced mid-level flow will spread across the Northern
Rockies from an upper low across the northwestern US today. A
cold frontal passage will bring rainfall across much of eastern
Montana and Wyoming this morning. Behind the cold front, a dry
continental air mass will overspread this region into the western
Dakotas, with relative humidity dropping as low as 15 percent amid
sustained winds 20-25 mph. Fuels within southern Montana into the
western Dakotas, where less rainfall is forecast, are sufficiently
dry to carry risk of Elevated fire weather concerns.

...Please see www.spc.noaa.gov/fire for graphic product...

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy1.html">Read more</a>
]]>
          </description>
          <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 16:25:37 +0000</pubDate>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy1.html/202404301946</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
          <link>https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy2.html</link>
          <title>SPC Day 2 Fire Weather Outlook</title>
          <description>SPC Day 2 Fire Weather Outlook
          <![CDATA[<br /><a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy2.html"><img src="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/day2fireotlk.gif" border="1" alt="Day 2 Fire Weather Outlook Image" hspace="1" vspace="1" width="815" height="555" align="center" /></a><pre>
Day 2 Fire Weather Outlook  
NWS Storm Prediction Center Norman OK
0202 PM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024

Valid 011200Z - 021200Z

...CRITICAL FIRE WEATHER AREA FOR EASTERN NEW MEXICO INTO THE FAR
WESTERN OK/TX PANHANDLES...

No changes. See previous discussion below.

..Bentley.. 04/30/2024

.PREV DISCUSSION... /ISSUED 0151 AM CDT Tue Apr 30 2024/

...Synopsis...
Dry and breezy conditions are expected across the southern High
Plains on Wednesday in response to a development of a lee cyclone,
as increasing mid-level flow overspreads the Rockies. Deeply mixed
profiles by the afternoon will yield single-digit relative humidity
amid sustained winds 20 to 25 mph across portions of eastern New
Mexico into the northern Texas Panhandle. Little recent rainfall
across this area has sufficiently dried fuels, with ERCs forecast to
be in the 75th percentile. This will support Critical fire weather
concerns, with broader Elevated fire weather concerns extending into
southeastern Colorado and the western Oklahoma Panhandle.

...Please see www.spc.noaa.gov/fire for graphic product...

</pre>
<a href="https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy2.html">Read more</a>
]]>
          </description>
          <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 19:03:28 +0000</pubDate>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.spc.noaa.gov/products/fire_wx/fwdy2.html/202404301946</guid>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>